Hello, and welcome to Lesson 14 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
大家好，欢迎来到本次与沃尔夫兰大学合作的微积分入门第14课。
The topic for this lesson is related rates.
本节课的主题是相关率。
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson. In most problems, there will be
首先，我们先来简单介绍一下本课的内容。在大多数问题中，会有
more than one thing that is changing in relation to something else. For example,
不止一个事物，它与其他事物的关系正在发生变化。例如：
you might have—of course time varies, but then two other things vary with time.
你可能会有--当然时间不同，但还有两样东西会随着时间而变化。
As a good instance of that, let’s talk about a ladder that’s falling along a side of a wall.
作为一个很好的例子，让我们来谈谈一个沿着墙的一侧下降的梯子。
That’s the ladder. It’s falling along the wall, and there are two things that are changing:
这就是梯子。沿着墙壁落下，有两样东西在变化。
there’s the height of the ladder from the top and the distance from the base of the ladder
梯子从上到下的高度和梯子从下到上的距离。
to the base of the wall. Both of these are changing as the ladder falls.
到墙的底部。这两种情况都是随着梯子的下降而变化的。
Of course, the rate at which the height is dropping and the rate at which
当然，高度下降的速度和
the distance is increasing are related. That’s the theme for today’s lesson: related rates problems.
的距离越来越大是有关系的。这就是今天课程的主题：相关率问题。
Let’s begin with an example, and that’s exactly the one we talked about earlier on of the falling ladder,
我们先举一个例子，这正是我们前面说的那个坠梯的例子。
but now we’ve got numbers in it. We have a ladder that’s 5 feet long, and it’s resting initially
但现在我们已经有了数字。我们有一个5英尺长的梯子，它最初是静止不动的
against a wall, and then it starts to slide down. Let’s say it slides down away from the wall
靠着墙，然后它开始下滑。比如说，它从墙上滑落下来
at a rate of 0.5 ft/s and the bottom of the ladder is 4 feet away from the wall at a certain point.
以0.5英尺/秒的速度，梯子底部距离墙面4英尺的某一点。
The question is how fast is the ladder sliding down at that time instant? The first step
问题是当时梯子瞬间滑落的速度有多快？第一步
in this case is to assign variables to whatever is changing in the problem. There are two things
在这种情况下，就是给问题中任何变化的东西分配变量。有两件事
that are changing. There is the height—y, let’s say—and the distance x.
变化的。比如说，有高度y和距离x。
Next I draw a picture of what’s happening. The picture is over here.
接下来，我画了一张图，把发生的事情画出来。图画在这里。
That’s the distance of the base, that’s the height and that’s the actual ladder over here.
那是底座的距离，那是高度，那是这边的实际梯子。
Okay. Now to find a relationship between x, y and 5 over here, you recall
好了，现在要找到&lt; i&gt;x&lt;/i&gt;、&lt; i&gt;y&lt;/i&gt;和这边的5之间的关系。现在要找到x，y和5之间的关系，在这里，你记得
the Pythagorean theorem from geometry, and that says that x^2 + y^2 = 5^2.
几何学中的毕达哥拉斯定理，说的是x^2+y^2=5^2。
That’s the relationship that we require between x and y. Now because we want to find the rates,
这就是我们要求的x和y之间的关系。现在因为我们要找率。
we differentiate that relation with respect to t. What you get back is 2x[t]x'[t] + 2y[t]y'[t] = 0.
我们对t的关系进行区分。你得到的是2x[t]x'[t]+2y[t]y'[t]=0。
Now keep in mind that x is 4 at that point, x' is 0.5, so you get back an equation which is
现在请记住，x在这一点上是4，x'是0.5，所以你得到的公式是
simpler than the earlier one, but it still ignored y’s. Then you recall the Pythagorean theorem,
比前面的更简单，但它仍然忽略了y的。然后你就会想起毕达哥拉斯定理。
and that lets you find y as being 3. Once we’ve got y, we can plug that back in over here
这样你就可以找到y是3。一旦我们得到了y，我们就可以把它插回这里了
to the earlier equation—that’s this one—and you get back the rate of change of y as being −0.666667.
到前面的方程--也就是这个方程，你就可以得到y的变化率为-0.666667。
The ladder is sliding down the wall at a rate of 0.67 ft/sec approximately. The question is
梯子以大约0.67英尺/秒的速度从墙上滑落。问题是
why is that sign negative? Well, it’s negative because the top of the ladder is actually going down.
为什么是负号？负号是因为梯子的顶部实际上是向下的。
Having solved that one problem, let’s set up a general strategy for solving such problems.
在解决了这一个问题之后，我们来建立一个解决这类问题的一般策略。
First, always try to understand the problem. Make sure you know what you are asked to do.
首先，一定要试着去了解问题。确保你知道要求你做什么。
Next, assign symbols to all variables—x, y, et cetera—in the problem.
接下来，给问题中的所有变量--x，y，等等分配符号。
Now to help yourself understand the problem better, draw a picture. It doesn’t have to be very elegant,
现在为了帮助自己更好地理解这个问题，画一张图。不一定要很优雅。
but it should be just enough for you to understand what you need to do. Next, the creative part:
但应该刚好够你了解你需要做什么。接下来，是创意部分。
find an equation that relates all the variables in the problem. Usually something from geometry
找到一个方程，将问题中的所有变量联系起来。通常是几何学上的东西
is going to help you to do that. Next differentiate the equation with respect to time using the chain rule.
就是要帮你做到这一点。接下来用链式法则对方程进行关于时间的微分。
That’s the key rule for today’s lesson. Now you already know a few variables,
这就是今天课程的关键规则。现在你已经知道了几个变量。
but you need to find any remaining unknown variables before you proceed. Once you have done that,
但你需要在继续之前找到任何剩余的未知变量。一旦你完成了这些工作，
then you substitute all the information that you’ve found out and solve for the true
然后，你把你找到的所有信息代入，并解出真正的。
unknown quantity in the problem. That’s the general strategy for this lesson.
问题中的未知量。这就是本节课的总体策略。
Let’s try and apply it to a few more problems. Here you have a spherical balloon
让我们试着把它应用到一些更多的问题上。这里你有一个球形的气球
that’s being filled at a rate of 50 cm^3/sec. The question is find the rate at which
以50 cm^3/秒的速度填充。问题是找出
the radius is increasing when the diameter is 25 cm. Now in this case, the volume and the radius
当直径为25厘米时，半径越来越大。现在，在这种情况下，体积和半径为
are both functions of time. Here’s a picture. It has the radius and the volume as being
都是时间的函数。这里有一张图片。它的半径和体积都是：
the variables for the problem. Next, you know from geometry that the volume of a sphere is (4/3)πr^3,
问题的变量。接下来，你从几何学中知道，球体的体积是(4/3)πr^3。
so that’s the relation. Next you differentiate that relation, and you get back an equation
所以这就是关系。接下来你对这个关系进行微分，就会得到一个方程。
relating v', r and r'. Of course you need to find what r is at that time t, but you know the diameter
有关v'，r和r'。当然你需要找到当时r是什么t，但你知道直径为
is twice the radius and the diameter is 25, so the radius at that time is 12.5.
是半径的2倍，直径是25，所以当时的半径是12.5。
You plug back all the information that’s known to you, and you find that
你把所有已知的信息都插回去，然后你会发现
the radius is increasing at roughly 0.025 cm/sec.
半径大约以0.025厘米/秒的速度增加。
For the third problem, let’s talk about a watchdog. There is a cat that is walking down a street
第三个问题，我们来说说看家狗。有一只猫，它正走在一条大街上
at 3 feet per second. Now, a dog is sitting and sees this cat and stays focused on it.
以每秒3英尺的速度。现在，一只狗正坐在那里，看到这只猫，并一直关注着它。
It doesn’t actually move, but then the dog is known to be 6 feet from the street
其实它并没有动，但后来知道狗是六尺见方的。
and the cat is 8 feet from that point. The question is how fast is the dog’s head turning?
而猫距离该点有8英尺。问题是狗的头转得有多快？
There are two things that are changing: the dog’s head is turning and the cat is moving away.
有两件事正在发生变化：狗头在转，猫在走。
The question is what do you do over here? Well, you first draw a picture.
问题是你在这里做什么？嗯，你先画一幅画。
That’s the angle of turning of the dog’s head, that’s the distance traveled by the cat down the street
那是狗头转动的角度，那是猫在街上走过的距离。
and this distance over here is given to us to be 6 feet. Now in this case
这里的距离是6英尺。现在在这种情况下
we have a right-angle triangle, so we can use the tangent of θ as the function x[t]/6.
我们有一个直角三角形，所以我们可以用θ的切线作为函数x[t]/6。
Once we have the relation over here, then you can differentiate it and you find that
当我们有了这边的关系之后，那么你就可以把它区分开来，你就会发现。
you have another relation for θ' now, but now you need to know what the secant of θ is.
你现在有了θ的另一个关系，但现在你需要知道θ的分词是什么。
Well, the point is that you have the Pythagorean theorem, so you use that to work out
重点是你有毕达哥拉斯定理，所以你用它来计算出：
the hypotenuse of the triangle at that time. It turns out to be 10. Use that to find the secant
当时三角形的斜边。结果是10。用它来求正割
like we’ve done over here. Once we’ve done that, you can plug in all the values
就像我们在这里做的那样。一旦我们做了这些，你就可以插入所有的值
and work out the rate at which the dog’s head is turning.
并计算出狗头转动的速度。
The dog’s head is rotating at 9/50 radians/sec or about 10.313 degrees/sec.
狗头以9/50弧度/秒的速度旋转，即约10.313度/秒。
Okay. On to the final problem for the lesson. Oil is being poured into an inverted cone
好了，现在进入本课的最后一道题。到了本课的最后一道题。油被倒入一个倒置的圆锥体中。
at a rate of 3 m^3/sec. That’s the rate of change of the volume. Given that the cone’s height is 10 m
以3米^3/秒的速度。这就是体积的变化率。考虑到圆锥体的高度是10米。
and the radius is 5 m, the question is find the rate at which the oil level is rising
且半径为5米，问题是求油位上升的速度。
when the oil is 5 m deep. You’ve got two variables over here: the volume and the height.
当油深5米时这里有两个变量：体积和高度。
That’s the picture for the problem. Now, you know from geometry that the volume of a cone
这就是这个问题的图片。现在，你从几何学上知道，一个圆锥的体积。
is given by (1/3)πr^2h, so that’s the equation for the problem.
由(1/3)πr^2h给出，所以这就是问题的方程。
Notice that you in fact have v, h and r, and in fact you want to work only with v and h,
请注意，您实际上有v、h和r，实际上您只想用v和h工作。
so we need to do a bit more work. Recall that when you studied similar triangles,
所以我们需要再做一些工作。记得在学习类似三角形的时候。
then you could find a relationship between the base and height. In this case,
那么你就可以找到底座和高度之间的关系。在这种情况下。
the radius is going to be half the height in the oil tank because by similarity,
半径要比油箱里的高度低一半，因为通过相似性。
any cone in the tank has a radius equal to half the height because you have the initial ones
罐中的任何锥体的半径都等于高度的一半，因为你有初始的锥体。
and the same ratio. Here’s the volume equation with that relationship.
和相同的比例。这是有这种关系的体积公式。
You differentiate it and plug in values, and you find that oil level is rising at 12/25π m/s.
你把它区分开来，插上数值，你发现油位以12/25π米/秒的速度上升。
Okay. That brings me to the end of the lesson, but our main objective over here
好了，我的课就到此结束了。这使我到了本课的最后，但我们的主要目标在这里。
was to solve problems which involved related rates. What we did was we set up
是为了解决涉及相关费率的问题。我们所做的是我们建立了
a general strategy for these problems. Then we solved a few of them, but in each case,
这些问题的一般策略。然后我们解决了其中的几个问题，但在每一个问题上。
what you need to do is to use the given information and then apply some geometry
你需要做的是使用给定的信息，然后应用一些几何图形
typically to get the equations required for the problem. That’s the end of this topic.
一般是为了得到问题所需的方程。这个题目就到此为止了。
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about linear approximations, but before we do that,
在下一节课中，我们会讲到线性近似，但在这之前。
do review this lesson. This was a pretty advanced application of calculus.
做复习这节课。这是一节相当高级的微积分应用课。
It’s just that we now know calculus so well that we can apply things quite easily,
只是我们现在对微积分了解得很透彻，可以很容易地应用一些东西。
but do review this lesson, look at the exercises and you should be ready for the next one
但是，复习一下这节课，看看练习，你应该为下一节课做好准备。
on linear approximations. I’ll stop over here. Thank you.
关于线性近似。我在这里停一下谢谢你了